Guide to the Bob Brown Oral History Project 2005-2010
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Bob Brown oral history project
2005-2010
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Oh 396
Brown, Bob, 1947 Dec. 11-
70 interviews
From 2005-2010, former Montana congressman Bob Brown conducted oral history interviews with a variety of political figures in Montana. The interviewees ranged from state legislators, lobbyists, attorneys and journalists, to Montana Constitutional Convention delegates and officials in administrative and financial branches of the Montana State government. A few highlights within the topics are Montana and the Anaconda Company, the recurring sales tax referendum, mining, elections, deregulation, and the legislative process over time.
Biographical Note
Bob Brown was born in Missoula, Montana, on December 11, 1947, but grew up on his family's grain and cattle ranch near Whitefish, Montana. He obtained a bachelor's degree in history from Montana State University-Bozeman in 1970 and a master's degree in education from the University of Montana-Missoula in 1988. He spent two years in the Navy, from 1971 to 1972, and married Susan Stoeckig in 1975. They have two daughters. Over 27 years, he taught government, history, and economics at three high schools in western Montana, and coached speech and debate teams.
At the age of 22 Brown became one of the youngest Montanans ever elected to the state House of Representatives. He served two terms in the House and was elected to the Senate in 1974. He served in the Senate through 1996, when term limits prevented him from running again. He was Senate president in his legislative session. Brown became a lobbyist for a telephone company, aluminum plant, and the Montana university system for four years and then was elected Montana Secretary of State in 2000 with 51 percent of the vote in a four-way race. Brown began a campaign for governor in July 2003 and faced three opponents for the GOP nomination. He won with 39 percent of the vote, a 16-point margin over the second-place finisher, but lost the election to Democratic candidate Brian Schweitzer.
In January 2005 Bob Brown returned to The University of Montana when he joined the O’Connor Center for the Rocky Mountain West as a senior fellow. Creating this oral history collection from 2005-2010 is just one of the projects he undertook in that position.
From 2005-2010, Bob Brown conducted oral history interviews with a variety of political figures in Montana. The interviewees ranged from state legislators, lobbyists, attorneys and journalists, to Montana Constitutional Convention delegates and officials in administrative and financial branches of the Montana State government. A few highlights within the topics are Montana and the Anaconda Company, the recurring sales tax referendum, mining, elections, deregulation, and the legislative process over time.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
The interviews were recorded by Bob Brown before deposit in the Archives and Special Collections.
As he completed the recording of one or more interviews from 2005-2010 Bob Brown donated them to Archives and Specials Collections.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Aasheim, Magnus, interviewee; Anderson, Forrest Howard, 1913-1989; Anderson, Jerome, interviewee; Aronson, J. Hugo (John Hugo), 1891-1978; Babcock, Tim, 1919-, interviewee; Bardanouve, Francis, 1917-2002--Influence; Bennett, Gordon, interviewee; Bishop, Alfred Lewis, interviewee; Blaylock, Chet, 1924-; Bradley, Dorothy M., 1947-, interviewee; Brown, Bob, 1947 Dec. 11-, interviewer; Brown, Dave, 1948-; Brown, R. Lewis, interviewee; Cobb, John, 1954-, interviewee; Crippen, Bruce D., 1932-, interviewee; Crippen, Lloyd, interviewee; Delano, John, interviewee; Eck, Dorothy, 1924- ,interviewee; Eskildsen, Leslie, interviewee; Fagg, Harrison, 1931-, interviewee; Fjare, Orvin B. (Orvin Benonie), 1918-, interviewee; Frank, Jake, 1915-, interviewee; Galt, Jack E., 1923-2007, interviewee; Galt, Louise R., 1923-, interviewee; Giacometto, Leo A., 1962-; Gilluly, Robert S., interviewee; Groff, William, 1920-; Gunderson, Jack, interviewee; Hall, John; Halligan, Mike, 1949-, interviewee; Hansen, Alec, 1941-, interviewee; Harp, John G., 1952-; Harper, Hal, 1948-; Harrington, Dan W. (Dan William), 1938-, interviewee; Haughey, James, interviewee; Hawks, Clyde, 1918-, interviewee; Himsl, Matt, 1912-2006, interviewee; Hoag, John T., 1914- interviewee; Jergeson, Greg, 1950-, interviewee; Judge, Thomas L., interviewee; Kemmis, Daniel, 1945-, interviewee; Kennedy, John F.(John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963--Influence; Kolstad, Allen, interviewee; Lahr, John, interviewee; Leuthold, John H.,1907-2005, interviewee; Lewis, David M., 1942-, interviewee; Lockrem, Lloyd C., interviewee; Lucas, James P., interviewee; Lynch, John D., 1947-, interviewee; Lynch, Neil, interviewee; Mansfield, Mike, 1903-2001; Marks, Bob; Marks, Robert L., 1932-, interviewee; Martz, Judy; Mathers, William, interviewee; Mazurek, Joe, interviewee; McGarvey, Dale, interviewee; McOmber, W. Gordon, interviewee; Mercer, John A., 1957-, interviewee; Metcalf, Lee, 1911-1978; Mockler, James, interviewee; Murray, James W., interviewee; Murray, Marshall, interviewee; Nichols, Norris, interviewee; Nordtvedt, Ken, 1939-; Norman, William J. (William James), 1922-, interviewee; Nutter, Donald Grant, 1915-1962; Ohs, Karl, 1946-, interviewee; Olsen, Arnold, 1916-1990; O'Neil, Carle, interviewee; Parks, Elin G., 1920-, interviewee; Patten, James, interviewee; Paynter, Judy, 1949-, interviewee; Pichette, J. Michael, intervieweee; Poore, Robert, interviewee; Racicot, Mark; Ramirez, Jack, 1939-; Rankin, Wellington Duncan, 1884-1966; Reagan, Ronald; Renders, Joe A., interviewee; Robinson, Ty, interviewee; Rolfe, Tom, interviewee; Rosell, Antoinette Fraser, 1926-, interviewee; Schweitzer, Brian, 1955-; Severson, Elmer D., 1922-; Shanahan, Ward, interviewee; Sheehy, John C., interviewee; Smith, Edward, interviewee; Schiltz, Jack M., interviewee; Schwinden, Ted, interviewee; Stephens, Stan, interviewee; Swysgood, Charles, 1939-; Thoft, Bob, 1929-; Tidball, Eugene C., 1930-, interviewee; Thomas, Fred, 1958- interviewee; Towe, Thomas, 1937-, interviewee; Turnage, Jean A., interviewee; Van Valkenburg, Fred R., interviewee; Vincent, John C., 1942-, interviewee; Walsh, Thomas James, 1859-1933; Wheeler, Burton K. (Burton Kendall), 1882-1975; Yardley, Dan, 1928-
Lynch, John D., 1947---family; Thomas, Fred, 1958---family; Walsh, Thomas James, 1859-1933--family; Wheeler, Burton K. (Burton Kendall), 1882-1975--family
Anaconda Company; Anaconda Company--Political activity--Montana; Harvard University--Alumni and alumnae--Interviews; Atlantic Richfield Co.; Great Falls Tribune; League of Women Voters of Montana; Mobil Oil Company--Employees; Montana Farmers Union; Montana. Constitutional Convention (1971-1972); Montana. Dept. of Fish and Game; Montana. Governor (1962-1969: Babcock); Montana. Governor (1960-1962: Nutter); Montana. Governor (1981-1989: Schwinden); Montana League of Cities and Towns; Montana. Legislature. House of Representatives; Montana. Legislature. House of Representatives--Appropriations Committee; Montana. Legislature. House of Representatives--Minority leaders--Interviews; Montana. Legislature. House of Representatives--Majority whips--Interviews; Montana. Legislature. House of Representatives--Speakers--Interviews; Montana. Legislature. Senate; Montana Power Company; Montana Power Company--Political activity--Montana; Montana. Supreme Court; Republican National Convention; Republican Party (Mont.); Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- )--Montana--Interviews; Montana Stockgrowers Association; Tea Party Patriots; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; University of Montana--Missoula--Alumni and alumnae--Interviews; University of Montana--Missoula--Associated Students; United States--Navy--Officers
Anaconda (Mont.)--History; Butte (Mont.); Butte (Mont.)--History--20th century; Butte (Mont.)--Politics and government--20th century; Glacier National Park (Mont.); McDonald, Lake (Mont.); Montana--Politics and government--20th century; Roosevelt County (Mont.)--History; Scobey (Mont.); Yellowtail Dam (Mont.)
Abortion--Law and legislation--Montana; Agriculture--Montana; Catholic men--Montana--Interviews; Coal leases--Montana; Coal--Taxation--Montana; Coal--Taxation--Wyoming; Coal mines and mining--Law and legislation--Montana; Coalbed methane; Constitutional conventions--Montana; Corporations--Political activity--Montana; Correctional institutions--Montana; Democracy--Montana--History; Deregulation--Montana; Elections--Montana; Elections--United States; Electric utilities--Deregulation--Montana; Electric utilities--Montana--History; Energy development--Law and legislation--Montana; Environmental law--Montana; Ex-legislators--Montana--Interviews; Finance, Public--Montana; Freedom of the press; Government and the press--Montana; Government, Resistance to--Montana--Garfield County; Governors--Montana; Governors--Montana--Election; Hostage negotiations--Montana; Hunting--Montana; Industrial relations--Montana; Journalism--Montana--History; Journalists--Montana; Labor unions--Political activity--Montana; Lawyers--Montana; Legislation--Montana--History; Legislative bodies--Montana; Legislators--Montana; Lieutenant governors--Montana; Lobbying--Montana; Lobbyists--Montana; Men--History--Interviews; Mines and mineral resources--Montana; Militia movements--Montana--Garfield County; Montana--Politics and government--20th century; Naval spouses--United States--Interviews; Officers' spouses--United States--Interviews; Political campaigns--Montana; Political campaigns--Montana--Butte; Political candidates--Montana--Interviews; Political science--Philosophy; Politicians--Montana; Sales tax--Law and legislation--Montana; Sales tax--Montana; Senators, United States Congress--Montana; Social action--Montana; Social movements--Montana; Tax assessment--Montana; Taxation--Montana; Term limits (Public office)--Montana; Wildlife management--Montana; Women--History--Interviews; Women--Political activity--Montana; Women--United States--Interviews; Women environmentalists--Montana--Interviews; Women legislators--Montana--Interviews; Women political activists--Montana--Interviews; Working class--Political activity--Montana
Oral histories--Montana; Interviews--Montana
Mines and Mineral Resources; Montana; Political Campaigns; Public Finance
- Interview with James Patten, 1 March 2005; OH 396-001; Sound Recording, digital, 412 MB, Wav; Transcript, 41 leaves
  Patten discusses his work as a lobbyist in Montana during the 1960s. He also talks about working with Governor Tim Babcock. He reminisces about Governors Donald Nutter and Ted Schwinden and other lobbyists with whom he worked.
- Interview with John Delano, 10 March 2005; OH 396-002; Sound Recording, digital, 308 MB, Wav; Transcript, 39 leaves
  Delano talks about his career as a lobbyist and describes some of the other lobbyists he knew. He discusses various changes in Montana politics from the 1950s to 2005 including the 1972 Constitutional Convention, term limitations, and the role lobbyists play in Montana politics. He also describes working with various Montana governors and provides anecdotes about each one.
- Interview with Ward Shanahan, 10 March 2005; OH 396-003; Sound Recording, digital, 374 MB, Wav; Transcript, 36 leaves
  Shanahan, a former railway association lobbyist, provides various anecdotes about his time working with the legislature including former governors, important issues, watering holes, the Anaconda Company and Montana Power Company, many influential legislators, and his relationship with Wellington Rankin.
- Interview with James Haughey, 15 March 2005; OH 396-005; Sound Recording, digital, 291 MB, Wav; Transcript, 24 leaves
  Haughey, a former legislator and a former lobbyist, describes the legislature in 1945 and onward, Anaconda lobbyists and hospitality room, governors and politicians, hunting trips with politicians, and sales tax reform and other political issues of his day.
- Interview with Carle O'Neil, 18 March 2005; OH 396-006; Sound Recording, digital, 372 MB, Wav; Transcript, 30 leaves
  O’Neil discusses how his career began in politics, various legislators who were influential, various important issues in the legislature, and influences of the Anaconda Company and Montana Power Company. He ends by describing his campaign for re-election.
- Interview with Dale McGarvey, 18 March 2005; OH 396-007; Sound Recording, digital, 396 MB, Wav; Transcript, 27 leaves
  McGarvey was a Democratic member of the Montana House of Representatives 1957-1959, a lawyer, and active in Montana public affairs. He discusses legislation he either supported or encountered in the House (education, occupational disease/silicosis/workers’ compensation, public utility districts), the Anaconda Company lobbyists and their influence in politics, his relationship with other Montana politicians, McCarthyist accusations against him, and suspected vote-buying by Montana corporations.
- Interview with Ty Robinson, 23 March 2005; OH 396-008; Sound Recording, digital, 419 MB, Wav; Transcript, 32 leaves
  Robinson discusses his recollections of Montana governors whom he met while working as a lobbyist, the influences of the Montana Power Company and Anaconda Company on Montana politics, and various significant politicians. He provides anecdotes of his time working in politics and ends by detailing the various roles of a lobbyist.
- Interview with W. Gordon McOmber, 23 March 2005; OH 396-009; Sound Recording, digital, 402 MB, Wav; Transcript, 41 leaves
  McOmber describes his affiliation with the Farmer’s Union as a young politician, the effects of the Montana Power Company and the Anaconda Company on Montana politics, and his terms in the legislature. He details his relationships with various legislators, governors, and lobbyists. He ends by giving a description of the legislature’s procedures before and after the new 1972 Montana constitution.
- Interview with Lloyd Crippen and R. Lewis Brown, Jr., 4 April 2005; OH 396-010; Sound Recording, digital, 434 MB, Wav; Transcript, 35 leaves
  Former lobbyist (Crippen) and attorney (Brown) for the Anaconda Company describe how they got connected with the Company, Crippen initially through his father-in-law and Brown after army service, law school and government work focused on labor relations. They recall experiences working for the Anaconda Company including reviewing and promoting Montana legislation, the Company’s hospitality room, relationships with legislators and other prominent figures, and other anecdotes of the time from 1955 through the 1970s.
- Interview with Jack Gunderson, 21 April 2005; OH 396-011; Sound Recording, digital, 417 MB, Wav; Transcript, 33 leaves
  Gunderson, a former Montana legislator, recalls being raised as a Democrat, the Farmers Union, the Farm Labor Coalition, the 1972 Constitutional Convention and its continuing impact, Anaconda Company influence, and various legislation. He describes his interactions with legislators, former governors, and his relationships with other Montana political figures.
- Interview with Joe A. Renders, 21 April 2005; OH 396-012; Sound Recording, digital, 253 MB, Wav; Transcript, 20 leaves
  Renders, a Montana lobbyist, public relations specialist, and journalist, describes his liberal political background, the personalities of politicians he has known in his career, the Anaconda Company’s involvement in state politics, control of the press in Montana, dynamics at the Great Falls Tribune, and advice for liberals of the future.
- Interview with Norris Nichols, 21 April 2005; OH 396-013; Sound Recording, digital, 419 MB, Wav; Transcript, 42 leaves
  Nichols, a former Montana legislator, describes his career in Montana politics and the family influences that persuaded him to run for the legislature. He goes on to describe his relationships with various Montana governors, politicians, and lobbyists before moving into a description of the Anaconda Company’s heavy influence on Montana politics for many decades.
- Interview with Matt Himsl, 22 April 2005; OH 396-014; Sound Recording, digital, 415 MB, Wav; Transcript, 24 leaves
  Himsl begins with his arrival in Kalispell, Montana, in 1945 and recalls his 60 years of community service including 24 years as a state legislator. He offers his impressions of and interactions with governors and legislators including Wellington D. Rankin and Governors Nutter, Aronson, and Babcock. Himsl includes anecdotes and discussions of issues including state sales tax and the Anaconda Company.
- Interview with Marshall Murray, 24 April 2005; OH 396-015; Sound Recording, digital, 419 MB, Wav; Transcript, 32 leaves
  Murray, former Montana legislator and floor leader of the Constitutional Convention, explains how he became interested in politics and the influences on his choice of party affiliation. He recalls working with former Montana governors and their personalities, influential legislators, lobbyists. The interview ends with Murray’s explanation of his role in the Montana Constitutional Convention and the process of getting the new document adopted.
- Interview with Robert S. Gilully, 27 April 2005; OH 396-016; Sound Recording, digital, 424 MB, Wav; Transcript, 34 leaves
  Gilluly begins with a discussion of his family’s experience in journalism and then discusses his experiences working for The Great Falls Tribune, the Missoulian, and the Ravalli Republican. He extensively addresses the issue of press control by the Anaconda Company. He talks about politicians he has known in Montana
- Interview with Allen Kolstad, 3 June 2005; OH 396-017; Sound Recording, digital, 313 MB, Wav; Transcript, 35 leaves
  Kolstad, former Montana legislator and lieutenant governor, reviews his time in politics in Montana including descriptions of influential legislators, issues, and lobbyists. He describes his campaign with Stan Stephens. Kolstad explains his involvement in national politics including relationships with Montana congressmen and Presidents Reagan, Bush Sr., and George W. Bush.
- Interview with Robert Poore, 27 April 2005; OH 396-018; Sound Recording, digital, 434 MB, Wav; Transcript, 29 leaves
  Poore, a Butte, Montana, attorney, discusses the interaction between the Anaconda Company and the city of Butte, Montana. He describes the Columbia Gardens Amusement Park. He discusses his relationship with the William A. Clark family (his wife’s grandfather was Francis Wharton, Clark’s “right-hand man”), the John Ryan family, the Cornelius Kelley family, and others. He talks about the Anaconda Company lobbyists and executives that he knew personally; his law practice in Butte and some of the cases he tried during the McCarthy era; and politicians he knew. He ends with comments on the relationship between the Anaconda Company, Montana Power, and Montana society.
- Interview with John Lahr, 27 April 2005; OH 396-019; Sound Recording, digital, 1.19 GB, Wav; Transcript, 57 leaves
  Lahr, former Montana Power Company lobbyist, discusses the workings of the Montana Power Company during the 1960s up until the 1980s. He tells stories of interaction between former legislators, governors, and other lobbyists and subjects such as territorial integrity, the Constitutional Convention, relationship with the Anaconda Company, and history of the Montana Power Company, providing an in-depth review of working as a Montana Company lobbyist.
- Interview with Tim Babcock, 29 April 2005; OH 396-020; Sound Recording, digital, 435 MB, Wav; Transcript, 29 leaves
  Babcock, former Montana governor, discusses his early political career, his relationship to and the death of Governor Don Nutter, his relationship with other local and national politicians (Forrest Anderson, Hugo Aronson, Dwight Eisenhower, Richard Nixon, Wellington Rankin, Mike Mansfield and others), and the influence of the Anaconda Company on Montana politics.
- Interview with Jerome Anderson, 4 May 2005; OH 396-021; Sound Recording, digital, 1.21 GB, Wav; Transcript, 60 leaves
  Anderson, Republican lawyer, oil lobbyist and Montana state legislator, discusses his involvement in state politics and his relationship with other state politicians, beginning with recollections of his father’s political career before turning to his own first congressional session in 1947. He also discusses some of the key issues during his terms in office such as the Yellowtail Dam controversy, gambling regulation, Anaconda Company and Montana Power Company political dealings, public utility districts, the formation of the Montana legislative council, sales tax, the 1972 Constitutional Convention, and coal and oil industry taxation. Anderson also describes the the mock congressional sessions that he organized in the 1950s and 1960s. Finally, Anderson notes changes in tenor in the state legislature from his early days to the present.
- Interview with J. Michael Pichette, 5 May 2005; OH 396-022; Sound Recording, digital, 421 MB, Wav; Transcript, 24 leaves
  Pichette was a Northwestern Corporation executive, a Montana Democrat with a long career in politics and public service, and a former executive director of the Democratic Party in Montana. He describes working for Montana Congressmen Olson and Melcher in Washington, D.C.; organizing political campaigns for and general impressions of Montana politicians, including Governor Ted. Schwinden, for whom he worked; the 1972 Constitutional Convention; the coal severance tax; changes in the Democratic Party; electrical deregulation; and his experiences working for Montana Power and Northwestern Corporation.
- Interview with John E. Sheehy, 8 June 2005; OH 396-023; Sound Recording, digital,402 MB, Wav; Transcript, 28 leaves
  Sheehy talks about his interest in politics at a young age and the political and social climate of Butte, Montana, when he was growing up. He describes Montana politicians he has known (Jerry O’Connell, Jim Murray, Wellington Rankin, Mike Mansfield, John Metcalf, Ted Schwinden, others). He talks about Anaconda lobbying techniques and personalities. He ends with a discussion of his time on the Supreme Court.
- Interview with Gordon Bennett, 8 June 2005; OH 396-024; Sound Recording, digital, 403 MB, Wav; Transcript, 26 leaves
  Bennett, a District judge and public servant, begins by discussing his childhood in Depression and drought era Scobey, Montana, mentioning the desperation that led to the election of communists in the 1930s. He talks about the rise of the Farmers Union in Montana and the business of farming in the state, the issue of press control by the Anaconda Company, his involvement in Lee Metcalf’s political campaigns, contrasts Metcalf and Mansfield, involvement in Forest Anderson’s campaign, and other Montana politicians he has known.
- Interview with James P. Lucas, 6 June 1995; OH 396-025; Sound Recording, 399 digital, MB, Wav; Transcript, 31 leaves
  Lucas, a former legislator, describes how he became interested in politics and his political philosophy. He discusses the lobbyists, Montana governors and fellow legislators with whom he worked. He also provides anecdotes about various pieces of legislation during his 1962-1972 stint in the Montana Legislature.